A lot of interesting stuff happens in the hallway.
It happens.
You know, you get to walk out of
a session and there's a collective experience that you just went through.
And so there will be a
hallway conversation that springs up discussing the material.
Welcome to Lifetime Management
in C++.
You're on the Back to Basics track.
If you are an expert in Lifetime Management,
you're welcome to stay, but please no heckling. This is going to be a tricky
at a back to basics level as it is.
So you may have to bear with us at some points.
It's a bit of a contradiction in terms.
Lifetime management is one of the more complex areas
of C++, but it is also something
that we should all be fairly familiar with
and able to understand what's going on.
Fortunately, we are gonna look at some things
that are gonna make it simpler.
We'll come on to that.
But I do wanna emphasize this warning.
C++ is a
complex language.
For many reasons, most of it historical,
but also a big focus on efficiency,
performance, and they're mixed with a bit of history as well,
really gives us a recipe for complexity.
And this is one of those areas that really shines through.
So C++ is complex.
But one of the things that's gonna help us to simplify this
is understanding that by default,
C++ is value -e -e -e -e -e -e -e -e -e -e -e -e
-e -e, like a value -first language.
It supports
other modes as well, and that's where the complexities start to come in.
But if we can
embrace the value-eased nature of C++, it's really going to help. Because
values are simple. And let's just look at an integer. We know how to use
integers.
We can just initialize it with a value.
We can assign it a new value if it's not const.
And if
it's in some scope, we know that at the end of that scope,
it's gone away.
It didn't have any
memory to manage, but you can no longer access it.
Simple, nice and easy to reason about.
That's what we want.
But even looking at integers, we can see there's a few phases
that they go through.
We've got the construction phase.
We're giving it an initial value.
We've
potentially got an assignment phase where we may assign it to a new value.
And that point
Okay, there's no actual destructors running, but there is a destruction phase there.
It's no longer accessible.
And if anything else was referring to it, say by point or a reference,
that's a problem
at that point because it's gone.
So those things apply to integers.
Obviously we could do the same thing with something like stood string.
Stood string models a value type in the same way that ints do.
So we go through those same phases.
We can construct strings with initial values.
We can assign them new values.
And of course, at the end of their scopes, they go out to scope,
they're no longer accessible.
But now there is actually a destruct
that runs and does some work.
One more, vector, same thing, same phases, everything is nicely managed.
It presents itself as a value type.
You can reason about it as a value type, even though under the hood,
there's actually
more complex stuff going on.
So these are our models to follow, ideally.
and none of this should be surprising so far I hope even if you're an
absolute beginner this is probably all very familiar and that's the point we
want these things to be non-surprising so how many people know this book effective
C++ so a good number but not everyone it's a bit bit of an older
book now C++
98 era but still a lot of wisdom in this in this book and the
follow -up book and one of
is this is in this is in this
this is
is
other quotes that I want to pull out, because I think it's really worthwhile reflecting
on these.
First of all, dear to the principle of least astonishment, we know how ints work.
And so we
know how strings work and vectors work to a large degree.
We're not surprised by how they
manage themselves. But also, recognizing that anything somebody can do, they will do. So
they'll throw exceptions, they'll assign objects to themselves, they'll use objects
before giving them values.
We've all seen this, I'm sure, but we need to be able to work with
these things.
And all three things that he mentions there are going to come up a bit
later
as it happens.
And the final quote from this, like there's only about three paragraphs that I'm
pulling these quotes from. It's actually quite dense. So as a result, make your classes
easy to use correctly and hard to use incorrectly. Really good advice. But to
follow through on that advice we need to really understand how lifetimes work and how
to manage them in C++ with the tools available.
So we looked at ints, strings, vectors, what
about pointers? They follow the same pattern. Pointers are also value types. There's nothing
about a pointer itself that inherently implies ownership. That's something we put on top of
it.
The pointers themselves, they're just an address, just a number.
Now value types.
And make
sure we remember that is also going to help us because pointers are one of
the
one of the things that makes this quite tricky so okay the three phases
construction assignment destruction well that's fairly easy to it's
holding your head it gets a little bit more messy from here there's eight
different ways that we can deal with these they break down a little bit so
construction well we've got the default constructor easy to understand
and then we're
we're going
going to go for you for
So, all of these, except for the custom constructor, are what we call special member
functions.
They have special properties.
Mostly that the compiler will generally write them for you if you give it space
to do so.
And this is a good thing.
This is something we want to happen.
But we need to understand how it happens or what it does when it does
do that.
So in the ideal case, we shouldn't have to implement any of these.
And that's when we get the gold standard.
And when we don't, we're going to need to know how to implement them ourselves.
So this is where that warning comes in.
This is where it starts to get complex.
But just bear in mind that when we go over this hump,
there's going to be a nice, easy run
the other side.
So something to look forward to.
So let's go down the rabbit hole.
If we go back to our gadget type, I introduced earlier with the pointer.
So simplest possible class is an empty class, of course.
can instantiate one of those as a value type on the stack.
It doesn't do anything, but it
works and it's easy to reason about, but not very useful.
So let's give it a data member,
an integer.
Again, we know how ints work.
So we also know how our gadget type works because it
effectively inherits what it can do from the integer.
What do I mean by that?
Well, let's ask
the
get the get a be a be
is a
be is be is a be be a be a be a be is a
be a be is a
be a be a be a be a be a
be a be a be a be a beater be the
if we don't give them a new and the initial
value they just take garbage from from the memory and then the class
doesn't change that automatically
the compiler has written a constructor for us here
a default constructor and it's effectively a
called the default constructor of an int.
It doesn't have one, so that's why it's effectively a no-op.
So, oh, and I should say,
just to save a little bit of clutter,
first of all, I'm making all of these things public,
so I don't have to write accesses, that sort of thing.
But I'll even go as far as, instead of a class
with a public first thing,
I'm just gonna go straight to a struct.
But I'm only doing that for exposition purposes,
because I'm gonna try to fit a lot of code on slides here.
All right, so let's add a constructor, default constructor, no arguments, and initializes
our integer to zero.
Hope you're familiar with how member initializer lists work.
Initializing I to zero, and that works.
Now we get a zero printed out, just as we expect.
We're actually got slightly better than our integer now.
We've got one that initializes itself.
we'll be a lot of the
a default value, we always want to initialize it with something valid.
We can do that as well with a custom constructor.
So now we pass in an integer, we use the member initializer list
to initialize it, and we're good.
But something that may be a little bit surprising here,
if you're not familiar with C++ at this level,
is that having done that, having written the custom constructor,
we now no longer have a default constructor.
So we try to default construct our gadget.
Now we're going to get a compiler error.
So the compiler generated default constructor is now disabled.
It no longer exists by writing a custom constructor.
It could be a little bit surprising.
And that's true, even if we reuse that default member initializer.
So this is the first of some principles to do with special member functions.
So the compiler will generate special member functions for you where it can.
we already just mention that.
But defining some of the special member functions and also the custom constructor, which remember
is not a special member function, can actually interplay with what actually gets
generated and maybe sometimes stop certain things from being generated or deleted.
So something to bear in mind and a little bit of a mind field to
navigate.
We're not going to go too deep on that at this level,
it's just something to be
and we'll we're going to be is we're going to do is we are we
are we are we are, we are, we are, and we are,
we are, we are, we are, we are, we are, we are,
we are, we are, we are we are, we are, we are,
we are not the compiler doing it, it's us.
In this case, it's, we're doing effectively the same thing as the default constructor would
have done, the compiler generated one.
So it's actually better to let the compiler still write that for you.
And you can do this,
that explicitly by writing equals default. Very useful to get the compiler generated
behavior back, even if it's the same as in this case.
Okay, so what if we copy one of
these gadgets?
We haven't written a copy constructor, but it just works.
Because again, the compiler is
generated a copy constructor for us that does the right thing.
Actually pretty good now.
And copy
you'll be there we're we're we're here to be there we're there we are we
are we are we don't
don't get
get we all we're going to be we're
we're the
the
integer at the top that we're incrementing in the constructor,
we're effectively giving ourselves an instantiation number
so we can try and keep track of things.
And I'm only doing this for the purpose
of keeping track of what's coming up.
Easy to lose track.
So don't do this at home, but that this should work.
And there's a explicitly implemented destructor.
Oh, this is what it prints.
So obviously the constructor runs first, prints the value
of I, and then we explicitly print I and the destructor runs.
Hopefully, as we expected, no surprises so far.
All right, now it starts to get more interesting.
We want to hold one of these gadgets in another class,
we're going to call widget.
We also got a string and an integer.
Now we said we like strings and integers, they're value types.
Nice and easy to reason about.
That shouldn't be a problem, should it?
And pointers, they're also value types.
So, what happens if we just print these members out straight away?
Well, the string has a default value, empty string.
The integer doesn't still, we already discussed that.
I know it does the pointer, so they're garbage values.
So again, we want to want to add a default constructor.
We're going to initialize our pointer to no pointer,
and now we get the expected results.
interesting so far, let's some some real values.
and our pointer to a new gadget.
We're creating on the heap and storing it in our pointer.
And that all works so far.
Or at least it prints the right results.
But you can see our gadget that we just created,
the constructor's fired.
Because we've seen that log out.
We haven't seen the destructor because, of course, we haven't deleted it.
I'm just going to rearrange that so that we can fit the next bits in.
That's just the same.
So of course we had a destructor.
That's what they're for.
cleaning things up.
Easy, yeah?
We delete in the destructor, and we're good.
And sure enough, that now prints out what we expect.
Gadgets being deleted, destructor's called,
memory's cleaned up.
Perfect, we can go home.
And not so fast, because what if we copy our widget?
Remember, the compiler is generated, a copy constructor for us,
that's just copying the values.
So, what's happened to the ownership?
We run that, not so good.
The pointer being free, but not allocated.
Yeah.
Because now we've got two destructors
trying to destroy the same pointer,
or the same heap object.
Okay, so we're going to add a copy constructor now.
So, you haven't done it before.
This is how you add a copy constructor.
I'll take it by const ref.
I can take it by ref as well.
Not advisable these days.
So always by cons ref.
And all we're going to do is just copy the members across,
as the compiler generated version would have done,
except for we're going to do something different
for the pointer.
I've got that bit for the moment.
We're going to create a new gadget on the heap
and construct that with the existing gadget so it gets a copy.
Straightforward, I think.
And that seems to work.
But we've only got one gadget in the constructor log, or only one gadget constructor
in the log,
should I say.
And that's because we didn't implement a copy constructor on the gadget.
So it's still using the compiler generated one.
So we can fix that.
And then we can see, I won't actually show the code, but now we get
that printed out as well.
So they add up.
We've got two constructors and two destructors.
So far, so good.
So that was copy construction.
What about assignment?
Now we're back to double deleted objects again
because we don't have an assignment operator.
Again, it was compiler generated, did the wrong thing.
We're gonna need to address that ourselves.
So we're gonna write an assignment operator,
copy assignment operator.
Like the copy constructor, it takes our widget by cons ref,
that does much the same thing.
It's going to assign values from the other object
to our members as the compiler generated one would have done
except for the pointer,
where we're going to create a new one on the heap,
evoke its copy constructor as we did before,
and we're good.
And it seems to work,
except, of course, we're not, we're missing a destructor again.
Because we created a new object and assigned it to the pointer,
the old object, now nothing's tracking it.
So what we should have done was delete the old one first.
Okay, so far so good.
But easy to miss if we weren't actually checking these logs.
Because it seemed to work, just leaked.
And there's the logs.
Okay, what about if gadget froze when you construct it, or if we're out of
memory?
of that they are going to go to get that that that that that that
that this
it.
So one way around that is to create our new object, assign it to a
temporary pointer,
then delete our old one, and then we can assign the new one in.
And that works.
So I didn't
show the throwing example, but that does actually solve that problem. Not a great solution,
but it does solve it.
Okay.
I put that off just the same slide again.
What about, ah,
sorry, misspoke.
It was a little bit subtle.
What I changed there was we're now assigning
our original widget to itself.
And you can do that.
It's perfectly legal.
And then it can happen.
Except our code now breaks.
It doesn't fully break.
Again, it seems to work.
But what it's now
doing is an unnecessary heap allocation and copy.
It's creating a new copy of our gadget.
She didn't need to do.
So we can guard against that.
Easy enough.
In some cases it's
more dangerous.
Here it was fairly benign.
Just a performance impact.
But we should do that as well.
And now we've got a little bit less code because we're emitting that copy.
Okay, it's a good time to take a pause and see where we got to
so far.
Because we've written a lot of code.
The font's getting smaller and the people at the back are probably finding it harder
to
read so this is our widget class and you can see we got a copy
constructor we've got a copy assignment operator and we have our destructor we've had
to write all of those things and the assignment operator was particularly
tricky to get right and maybe we're not even quite done yet but we had
to do all of
that because we introduced this point of a head ownership of some memory with
to be we're
we're
Follow the rule of three.
Now there may be some of you thinking,
oh, the rule of three, that's outdated.
C++11, we've now got move constructors
and move assignment operators.
Now it's the rule of five.
And we will get there, I promise.
But it's worth still thinking about the rule of three
because actually the move operators, operations
are not necessary all of the time.
So don't make life hard for yourself if you don't need to.
the rule of three can still get you there okay um got
got what i'm showing here just zooming in
that's right we're not quite done on the assignment operator but a little bit more
we can do
this is where we got to the reason i put the copy constructor up as
well is just to note that
there's maybe a bit of redundancy there the code duplication it's doing the same thing
in slightly
different ways it'd be nice if we could we could share that somehow and we
can
can.
This is how we might do it.
So we're going to create a temporary widget,
copy constructed from our incoming other widget, and then we're going to swap all the
members
in.
So swapping is just going to take the value from one, put in us,
and then take our value and put it in the other one.
A couple of things to note here.
First of all, we've got that using stood swap.
It's not just because I'm being lazy,
although I am. There's actually a real reason to do that. And that's because some
types may have their own specialization of swap in their own namespace.
And if they do,
doing it this way, we've got stood swap to fall back on,
but otherwise it's going to
choose the one it finds by argument dependent look up.
That's another topic we're not going
to go on to now.
So if there doesn't mean anything to you, just trust me on this.
When you do these swaps, do using stood swap first,
and then do an unqualified swap,
and it should always do the right thing.
So that's another little rule to bear in mind.
The other thing to bear in mind here is,
you might be thinking if you know stood swap,
that it will actually do a member-wise swap.
So it could do swap on the whole widget.
The problem is we don't actually have a move constructor here,
and stood swap is implemented in terms of move.
So it's going to call the copy constructor,
which we're sort of implementing here.
So it's going to be a recursive call.
So for now, we're going to do member-wise swap.
If we implement a move constructor,
we may be able to implement this differently,
but we're not there yet.
Another thing to note here, nice side effect,
is this gives us what we call the strong exception safety guarantee.
That means that if an exception is thrown at any point
during this assignment, we are guaranteed
to have the original value that we had.
we're not in some halfway state.
The weaker form, the weak exception guarantee,
as long as we're in a valid state,
we're okay.
And most of the time that's okay.
Strong guarantee is quite nice.
And it just drops out of this.
This is called the copy and swap medium.
Okay, let's carry on.
Go back to our fuller example.
Then we've tackled the rule of free,
the copy operations.
Let's have a look at movement, moving.
So move semantics, our value references, another relatively complex and advanced topic.
I'm going to have to assume that you will have some familiarity with it.
If not, there are other sessions that will fill you on that,
but bear with us.
So if we do stood move on our first widget, we are saying this is,
we can actually take the
guts of that object now and use it ourselves.
We don't have to make copies.
So, if we do that with our current implementation, it actually works.
It's fine.
This is what I was saying earlier.
If you do a move, you don't have a move
constructor or move assignment operator, it's going to fall back to the copy operations,
and they'll just work.
They're just going to be less efficient.
So, let's be more efficient,
and implement a move constructor.
So, here's a move constructor.
We can do a member.
remember why it's move, the string, the int, and the pointer.
That all seems to work.
It compiles.
It doesn't actually do the right thing at runtime.
Hopefully obviously when you do something with that, keep allocated object again.
Move in the pointer.
It's just the same as copying it in this case.
So we didn't actually move
the resource itself. In this case, it's actually a fair.
really really, really really really really, really, really, really, really, really,
, really, really, really, really, really,
going, really, really,
a good, a good, a good, a good,
copy, and delete, a case of a pointer.
Sorry, not, delete, a, set it to a null pointer.
So now the outgoing moved from widget,
no longer has an object it's trying to delete.
So we don't give that double delete.
And you can see that's actually less in the log now,
we're not copying things, there's less operations going on.
Nice.
Okay, that, having to do that
null pointer assignment in the body of the constructor maybe feels a bit ugly,
feels a bit off
somehow.
Everything else is done in the initializer list.
Well, we can do that too.
And actually, the
modern idiom is to use stood exchange. If you're not familiar with stood exchange, pretty
I
and some other types, they would actually check that because vectors have to move things
around
and if they can't actually move them, they're going to copy them.
So make sure you do put
no accept there.
It's one of the few places that you should just routinely put no accept.
Move constructors and as we're going to see, move assignment operators. Another little
thing to remember. Okay. Talking of move assignment operators, let's try move assigning.
So we did Stub move and assign the result to a pre-existing widget.
Again, we haven't implemented it yet, but it just works because it's falling back on
copy.
So let's implement the move assignment operator.
Here's our first step.
So we move our string, but actually need to move the integer,
copy and move with the same thing for ints.
And again, we can use Stude Exchange for our pointer.
Same reason as before.
great okay and also no accept for the same reason all right worked
worked first time great
um previously for the copy assignment operator we sort of evolved it to that copy
and swap
idiom could we do the same thing here like a copy and move what we
could
but it turns out to just not be worth it because remember copy and swap
does
and the main, and to to to to to to be to to to to
to and to to to and to to to to and to to be,
I am, I am and I am, I am, I am, I am,
I am, I am, I am I don't, I don't need that.
And it's actually a fairly simple code.
So it's not worth using a copy and move idiom for the move assignment operator,
even though it's tempting to do so.
The whole point of the move operation is,
is to maximize performance most of the time.
So don't pessimize it by using copy and move.
Okay, we got through quite a lot already.
Let's just take stock.
And just, there's too much code to fit it all on one screen.
So I'm just gonna summarize it here.
You can see that we've implemented
all of the special member functions.
Copy constructor, move constructor,
copy assignment operator,
operator, move assignment operator, and the destructor. And previously we implemented three
of them for the rule of three.
Because we wanted move semantics, we added two more,
and that gives us, finally, the rule of five.
So again, the rule of five.
If you need one
of these and you want move semantics, then you probably need all five.
Again, if you
don't need to optimize for moves, the rule of three is actually still available to
need to implement three.
It's a bit less work.
Because this stuff, it can be hard
to get right.
Hopefully you've seen that by now.
But you know what?
There's a better
answer, and it's right in front of us.
Let's simplify our widget a bit.
If we just
take out that pointer for the resource management, we've got pure value types. Well, simple
value types now, the string and an integer.
And instead of all that C out stuff,
save a bit of code because I can actually put all of the operations now
in one bit of
sample code. So this is doing construction, copy construction, assignment, move construction,
move assignment.
I'm even doing a couple of logging some moves from states.
And that all
gives the results that you would expect.
You can check.
It's a little bit tricky to match it up.
Those spaces are the moves froms, empty strings. Not guaranteed to be that way.
So, it is a mind machine.
Nice and simple.
We don't have to write anything.
That's
what we want.
Can we get the management of our memory and still have this?
The answer is yes,
maybe.
Let's do the yes part.
That's the best bit.
So we could use a unique pointer to
to manage the memory for us.
This is not exactly the same as we have before.
This doesn't actually have different
this is
here.
We don't have any copy operations because it's unique ownership.
So as I mentioned before,
the properties of your data members, the most constrained form in terms of special member
functions, you sort of inherit those. So because we're using unique pointer, we now have
unique ownership semantics. Unless we explicitly
implement those copy operations, which we could do the same way as before,
which is still
a lot less code.
So that's good.
I wouldn't show that.
We've already seen it.
Oh, I meant
to show that as well.
We can see our gadget constructor in there as well now, but still
a lot less going on.
So that's a big win.
And in fact, this leads to the third rule
we want to talk about. We really want us to strive to
only have value types or managers, and I'm going to define managers in a moment,
but this
will give us the rule of zero.
And really the rule of zero is what you should be trying
to follow as close to 100 % at the time as possible,
because the rule of zero says, well, in
summary, always strive to have the compiler generated special member functions do the right
thing. And if you only have value types and managers, the compiler generated special
member functions will do the right thing. You won't have to worry about them.
that sometimes you do have to explicitly manage memory or some other resource,
a file, network, sockets, whatever it is.
The special member functions are there for a reason,
but they should only be used for those specific cases.
If there's not an existing library type in the standard library,
even a third party library, always reach for those first.
You can still write your own and then you have to follow the rules we
just talked about, but don't mix it.
So, before we had an integer, a string, and managing some raw memory.
And that meant that we didn't get the advantage of the compiler generated handling of
our
integer and our string.
We had to do it explicitly.
So always have your own manager types.
If you do need to manage a resource, have a manager type.
So a manager type is a generalization of something like unique pointer, shared pointer, anything
that that
that
that I put in at the end, this saved me recreating it,
where I summarize all the different types of managers,
and more generally, the categories of type
with respect to resource management.
So the simplest ones at the top are value types,
simple direct values, ints, strings, that sort of things.
They follow the rule of zero.
Or rather, if you use them, then you follow the rule of zero.
views are non -owning managers so they do actually deal with raw memory usually like
string view
or span md span so they they also follow the rule of zero because they
don't actually manage ownership
but then you get to polymorphic base classes they're a little bit different we didn't
really talk
about those you probably will need to follow the rule of five or some variation
on it there's an
asterisk i'm not going to go into the the details that i went
into in the blog post.
Basically follow the rule of five for polymorphic base classes.
So anything with virtual, particularly pure virtual member functions that you derive from.
Then we get into the managers.
So the simplest one is a scoped manager.
So a scoped manager is non -copyable and non -moveable, which means you are following
the rule of five,
but you're doing it by deleting copy and move operations.
So it is simpler.
A delete with the delete keyword equals delete counts as an implementation so you're following
the rule of five for scope managers so they're the simplest types and maybe the
least useful unique managers perhaps the most useful so unique pointer is an example of
a unique manager so has unique ownership and move move only semantics so again we
follow the rule of five but we disable or delete
Go.
the copy operations and we implement move and finally more generally a general
manager that does have move hand copy and follows the rule of five value types
are maybe examples of general managers like stood string stood vector you can
treat them as value types but they're also implement that resource management
for you.
There are examples of general managers that aren't value types in the same way,
like shared pointer.
Shared pointer, you can copy, you can move, but it's not a value type because
it's got shared ownership.
So there are some more advanced levels here that I'm going to stop
short of going into in depth, but do read the blog post if you want
to find out more.
And with that, I've actually come to the end of what I wanted to share
with you.
So
much and we've got plenty of time if you've got questions because there's lots
that I papered over there any questions so Mike someone come okay yes
yes thanks for
the talk the slide just before the rule of five was introduced there it looked
like there's a missing destructor but I wasn't sure if that was a typo or
if
that was expected behavior hold on sorry I got distracted trying to find a
slide I think it's in front of us
Sorry, yeah, for this.
That one, oops.
Yeah, just before this.
Actually, this one, yeah, or the previous one.
This one, yeah, okay.
So your question, okay.
Just, is the missing destructor number two here,
expected behavior, or is that a typo?
Sorry, didn't quite catch up.
Is the missing destructor here expected behavior,
or is that a typo?
There's a constructor for number two,
And then there's no destructor for number two ever.
You are right.
And that is expected because this is a move operation.
So we're transferring ownership.
So the destructor for gadget only happens once, but you get the move operation.
Okay, thank you.
Hi.
So I was curious if you could elaborate on situations between when you'd use rule
of three versus rule of five.
the
be be be like be like be like be like be like be like be
like be like be like be like be,
, be like be like, be like,
be like,
is,
I'm going to lead you to implement
move semantics.
In particular,
I mentioned the
unique ownership managers.
So they are move only.
So the only way you can use them is to move.
Of course, you're,
probably doing that for performance purposes.
But if you're using, say, a unique pointer,
then you have now move semantics.
So, yeah, off the top of my head,
I can't think of a more concrete example, but yeah.
Hi, I've seen implementations of the copy constructor
where the temporary object
was created implicitly by not passing a reference
into the copy and I'm sorry, the assigned operator
by passing the assigned object
into it using a copy constructor as opposed to creating one on stack.
Is that considered bad form or just not want something that you want to show?
We try to piece together what you said if I got it right.
If you go to the slide that shows the assignment operator.
You talked about explicitly calling the copy constructor?
So instead of the assignment operator receiving a const reference to an object.
Oh, receiving a value.
Sorry.
Yeah, we're receiving a value.
So let me find the slide where I showed.
Well, that's, yeah.
That's one of the examples of the copy and swap idiom.
So I think this is what you're talking about.
So rather than taking other in by const ref and then copying it into temp,
we basically
by value and now it is our copy.
Non-const and by value.
Non -const and by value.
That is now playing the role of our temp.
I mean it should
boil down to the same code.
It's one nest line.
And from an implementation perspective, it seems
to be simpler.
The one reason I would say, I'm not saying don't use it.
It's a perfectly
valid idiom as well.
But the one thing to keep in mind is you're now saying something on your
interface about what your implementation is doing.
So when you have the const ref from a caller's perspective,
it's an operator anyway, so you don't really call it
explicitly.
But still, when you're looking for the interface,
oh, this is just taking a reference in by the const ref.
it's not going to do anything with it.
When you have a value type there, that's just saying something
slightly different.
99.9% of the time, that's not going to matter.
And so you can probably do that.
one thing to keep in mind it does actually change the interface a little bit
but it's
supposed to be valid yeah thank you i also have a question about the same
slide um when the restructure of the temp widget gets called i assume um the
last swap there it takes the gadget that's within this sorry this one did you
say yes this slide the last swap and it will swap it into temp
ability of cleaning up to the temporary object.
If we go back to this version, we had to explicitly
delete our previous heap allocated object. And that was causing a bit of problem because,
you know, what happens if an exception is thrown?
We need to worry about that.
If an exception
was thrown, although by moving the order, did I have that one?
Did I actually edit that
slide?
Did I?
If you do the delete, oh, no, that is right.
Yeah.
So we
We've got the temporary variable for the pointer.
Then we delete and then we assign.
And if an exception is thrown in the middle,
we'd be in a valid state,
but not the original state necessarily,
because we've already changed name and age.
Again, we can play with the ordering a bit,
but the copy and swap idiom just takes care
of all that for us, does with the cleanup for us,
just simplifies thinking about it.
All we have to do is the swaps.
So even though the amount
of code is similar, the complexity is much less.
So that's the advantage of copy and swap.
There's a slight overhead or there may be,
maybe optimized out, more so on the move and swap,
that's the one to avoid.
But copy and swap for assignment operators,
I still routinely do that, but you can do it by hand.
Did that answer your question?
Yeah, thank you.
Thanks for the talk.
So I was curious when you recommend explicitly defaulting
one of the rule five you discussed?
When to explicitly defaults?
Good question actually, I touched on it a little bit
where I said, well, if you're doing the same thing anyway,
just let the compiler write it for you.
So the general rule is, if the compiler can write it,
you should let it write it.
There are some cases where, as we said,
defining some special member functions,
or the custom constructor will suppress that generation,
but you can get it back.
by using equals default.
And in some cases by following the rule of five
or the rule of three,
you say, well, I need an assignment operator here,
but I know the compiler is gonna do the right thing.
So just default it.
Even if it was gonna write it anyway,
you're being explicit about the fact
that you follow the rule of three or the rule of five.
So that's the other case where you might use it,
even though you didn't even need to.
So I do advise then that for the rule of five,
we either default them, implement them, or delete them
constantly to make it more verbose, what we're trying to accomplish.
It's a little bit more verbose, but I think it's more expressive.
In that blog post, I do go into a little bit of a more advanced
topic where there
are some cases you might want to go against that rule, but it's effectively following
another
rule.
So have a look at, there are some exceptions, but generally for this sort of
thing.
Because if you're reviewing somebody else's code and you say, oh, there's some resource
management going on here.
How do I know they've done it right?
It's a good sign if you can see they've considered the rule of five.
It's a good starting point.
So you want to signal that, yeah, I've considered all of these and I think
the compiler
is doing the right thing.
I've not just left it to chance.
That's the key.
Awesome.
Thank you.
No problem.
Any other questions?
Okay, great.
Then I think we can have an early termination.
Thank you.